The Kraken, a beast so terrifying
"الكراكين " وحش مرعب جداً
it was said to devour men and ships and whales,
وقيل أنّه قد افترس العديد من الرجال والسفن والحيتان
and so enormous it could be mistaken for an island.
وهو ضخم جدا، لدرجة أنّه قد يُعتقد انه جزيرة.
In assessing the merits of such tales,
ولتقييم مصداقية هذه المقولات،
it's probably wise to keep in mind that old sailor's saw
قد يكون من الحكمة أن نضع في اعتبارنا أنّ البحّارة القدماء رأوا
that the only difference between a fairytale and a sea story
أنّ الفرق الوحيد بين القصص الخيالية و قصص البحر
is a fairytale begins, "Once upon a time,"
هو أنّ القصص الخيالية دائما ما تبدأ بـ "كان يا مكان "
and a sea story begins, "This ain't no shit." (Laughter)
أمّا قصص البحر فتبدأ بـ"هذا ليس مجرد هراء" (ضحك)
Every fish that gets away
كل سمكة استطاعت الهرب
grows with every telling of the tale.
تنمو مع كل رواية للقصّة.
Nevertheless, there are giants in the ocean,
بالرغم من ذلك، يوجد عمالقة في المحيطات،
and we now have video proof,
ولدينا اليوم إثبات بالفيديو،
as those of you that saw the Discovery Channel documentary are no doubt aware.
أمّا الذين شاهدوا منكم قناة ديسكفري الوثائقيّة فهم يعلمون ذلك بلا شك.
I was one of the three scientists on this expedition
لقد كنت واحدة من ثلاثة علماء في هذه الرحلة الاستكشافية
that took place last summer off Japan.
التي كانت في الصيف الماضي قبالة اليابان.
I'm the short one.
أنا الأقصر بينهم.
The other two are Dr. Tsunemi Kubodera and Dr. Steve O'Shea.
والعالمان الآخران هما د.تسونيمي كوبوديرا و د.ستيف أوشيا.
I owe my participation in this now-historic event
أنا مدينة بمشاركتي في هذا الحدث التاريخي حاليّا
to TED.
لـTED.
In 2010, there was a TED event called Mission Blue
سنة 2010، كان هناك حدث لـTED باسم "المهمة الزرقاء"
held aboard the Lindblad Explorer in the Galapagos
تمّ على متن سفينة "ليندبلاد" في "غالاباغوس"
as part of the fulfillment of Sylvia Earle's TED wish.
كجزء من تحقيق أمنية سلفيا إيرلي من TED.
I spoke about a new way of exploring the ocean,
تكلّمت عن طريقة جديدة لاكتشاف المحيط،
one that focuses on attracting animals instead of scaring them away.
طريقة تعتمد على جذب الحيوانات بدلا من تخويفها و إبعادها.
Mike deGruy was also invited,
و كان مايك ديجري أيضا مدعوّاً،
and he spoke with great passion about his love of the ocean,
وتكلّم بشغف كبير عن حبّه للمحيط،
and he also talked to me about applying my approach
وأخبرني أيضاً عن تطبيق أسلوبي
to something he's been involved with for a very long time,
على أمر انخرط فيه منذ وقت طويل،
which is the hunt for the giant squid.
وهو ملاحقة الحبار العملاق.
It was Mike that got me invited to the squid summit,
وقد كان مايك هو سبب دعوتي إلى مؤتمر الحبّار،
a gathering of squid experts at the Discovery Channel
وهو تجمّع لخبراء الحبار في قناة ديسكفري
that summer during Shark Week. (Laughter)
في ذلك الصيف وخلال أسبوع القرش. (ضحك)
I gave a talk on unobtrusive viewing
قدّمت حديثاً عن العرض المخفي
and optical luring of deep sea squid
و الاستدراج البصري للحبّار في أعماق البحار
in which I emphasized the importance
و الذي أكّدت فيه على أهميّة
of using quiet, unobtrusive platforms for exploration.
استخدام قاعدات هادئة مخفيّة للاستكشاف.
This came out of hundreds of dives I have made,
و اكتشفت هذا عن تجربتي في الغوص لمئات المرات،
farting around in the dark
والتّخبط بلا هدف في الظلام
using these platforms,
باستخدام هذه القاعدات،
and my impression that I saw more animals
و النّتيجة هي أنّني رأيت أكثر حيوانات
working from the submersible
عند عملي في الغواصّة
than I did with either of the remote-operated vehicles.
أكثر مما رأيته في المركبات التي تعمل بالتّحكم عن بعد.
But that could just be because the submersible has a wider field of view.
وقد يكون السبب وراء هذا هو أن الغواصة لها مجال رؤية أوسع.
But I also felt like I saw more animals
ولكن أشعر أيضاً أنني قد رأيت حيوانات أكثر
working with the Tiburon than the Ventana,
عندما عملت في تيبرون أكثر ممّا رأيته في فينتانا،
two vehicles with the same field of view
وهي مركبات بنفس مجال الرؤية
but different propulsion systems.
ولكنّها تختلف في نظم التّسيير.
So my suspicion was that it might have something to do with the amount of noise they make.
وكنت أشك أن ذلك له علاقة بكمية الضجيج التي تصدرها المركبات.
So I set up a hydrophone on the bottom of the ocean,
لذلك قمت بوضع سماعات مائية في قاع البحر،
and I had each of these fly by at the same speed and distance
وجعلت كل واحدة من هذه المركبات تطير بنفس السرعة و المسافة
and recorded the sound they made.
وسجّلت الصوت الذي تصدره.
The Johnson Sea-Link -- (whirring noise) --
مركبة جونسون سي لنك --(صوت طنين)--
which you can probably just barely hear here,
والتي بالكاد تسمعون الصوت الذي تصدره هنا،
uses electric thrusters -- very, very quiet.
تستخدم دافعات كهربائية -- هادئة جداً.
The Tiburon also uses electric powered thrusters.
وتستخدم التيربون أيضاً دافعات تعمل بالطاقة الكهربائية.
It's also pretty quiet, but a bit noisier. (Louder whirring noise)
وهي هادئة أيضاً و لكنها أكثر ضوضاء. (صوت طنين أْعلى)
But most deep-diving ROVs these days use hydraulics
ولكن معظم مركبات الغوص ذات التحكم عن بعد هذه الأيام تستخدم الوحدات الهيدروليكية
and they sound like the Ventana. (Loud beeping noise)
ويشبه صوتها الفانتانا. (صوت تنبيه عالي)
I think that's got to be scaring a lot of animals away.
و أعتقد أن هذا السبب الذي يخيف الحيوانات و يبعدها.
So for the deep sea squid hunt,
و لصيد الحبار الموجود في عمق البحار،
I proposed using an optical lure
أقترح استخدام إغراء بصري
attached to a camera platform
مثبت بقاعدة الكاميرا
with no thrusters, no motors,
بدون دافعات و لا محركات
just a battery-powered camera,
فقط كاميرا تعمل بالطاقة
and the only illumination coming from red light
و الإضاءة الوحيدة قادمة من الضوء الأحمر
that's invisible to most deep-sea animals
والتي لا تراها الحيوانات في أعماق البحر
that are adapted to see primarily blue.
التي في الأساس تعوّدت على رؤية اللون الأزرق.
That's visible to our eye,
وهذا نستطيع رؤيته بعيننا المجردة،
but it's the equivalent of infrared in the deep sea.
ولكنه يعادل الأشعة الحمراء في أعماق البحار.
So this camera platform, which we called the Medusa,
وقاعدة الكاميرا هذه، والتي تسمى أيضاً ميدوسا،
could just be thrown off the back of the ship,
يمكن أن ترمى في نهاية السفينة
attached to a float at the surface with over 2,000 feet of line,
مثبتة في العوامة على سطح البحر بأكثر من 2000 قدم من الأسلاك
it would just float around passively carried by the currents,
و تطفو في جميع الأنحاء بلا مقاومة محمولة التيارات
and the only light visible to the animals in the deep
و الضوء الوحيد المرئي للحيوانات في القاع
would be the blue light of the optical lure,
هو اللون الأزرق للإغراء البصري،
which we called the electronic jellyfish, or e-jelly,
و الذي نطلق عليه اسم قنديل البحر الالكتروني او الجلي الالكتروني،
because it was designed to imitate
لأنّها صمّمت لمحاكاة
the bioluminescent display
شاشة العرض الضيائية البيلوجية
of the common deep sea jellyfish Atolla.
لقنديل البحر "أتولا" الشائع في أعماق البحار.
Now, this pinwheel of light that the Atolla produces
و مروحة الضوء هذه التي تنتجها الأتولا
is known as a bioluminescent burglar alarm
تعرف بجهاز إنذار ضد السرقة ضيائي بيلوجي
and is a form of defense.
وهو نوع من أنواع الدفاع.
The reason that the electronic jellyfish worked as a lure
والسبب في عمل قنديل البحر كإغراء
is not because giant squid eat jellyfish,
هو ليس بسبب أن البحار العملاق يأكل القناديل،
but it's because this jellyfish only resorts to producing this light
بل لأن القنديل يلجأ إلى إنتاج هذا الضوء فقط
when it's being chewed on by a predator
عندما تفترسه الحيوانات المفترسة
and its only hope for escape
وهو مجردّ أمل للهروب
may be to attract the attention of a larger predator
لكي يشد انتباه الحيوانات المفترسة الأكبر
that will attack its attacker
والتي ستهاجم مهاجمها
and thereby afford it an opportunity for escape.
و بذلك سيكون لها فرصة للهروب.
It's a scream for help, a last-ditch attempt for escape,
فهو صرخة لطلب المساعدة و محاولة أخيرة للهروب
and a common form of defense in the deep sea.
وشكلاً شائعاً من أشكال الفاع في أعماق البحار.
The approach worked.
و هذه الطريقة نجحت.
Whereas all previous expeditions had failed to garner
في حين أن جميع البعثات السابقة فشلت في كسب
a single video glimpse of the giant,
لقطة فيديو واحدة العملاق،
we managed six, and the first triggered wild excitement.
و لكننا تمكّنا من أخذ خمس لقطات و أول لحظة حماس جامح.
Edith Widder (on video): Oh my God. Oh my God! Are you kidding me?Other scientists: Oh ho ho! That's just hanging there.
إيديث ويدر (في الفيديو): يا إلهي. يا إلهي! هل تمزح معي؟ العلماء الآخرون: أوه! إنه فقط يتسكع هناك.
EW: It was like it was teasing us, doing a kind of fan dance --
إيديث ويدر: كأنّه يريد أن يغيظنا برقصة المروحة --
now you see me, now you don't --
الآن تراني، و الآن لا تراني
and we had four such teasing appearances,
وكان لدينا أربع أشكال إغاظة مثل هذا القبيل،
and then on the fifth, it came in and totally wowed us.
وفي الخامس، جاء و أبهرنا تماماً
(Music) Narrator: (Speaking in Japanese)
(موسيقى) الراوي: (يتكلم باليابانية)
Scientists: Ooh. Bang! Oh my God! Whoa!
العلماء: اووه. يا إلهي! واو!
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
EW: The full monty.
إيديث ويدر: ذي فول مونتي.
What really wowed me about that
الشيء الذي أبهرني حقاً حول هذا
was the way it came in up over the e-jelly
هو طريقة اقترابه لقنديل البحر الالكتروني
and then attacked the enormous thing next to it,
ومن ثم مهاجمة الشيء الهائل بجانبه،
which I think it mistook for the predator on the e-jelly.
والذي أعتقد أنه ظنّه المفترس عوض قنديل البحر الالكتروني.
But even more incredible was the footage shot
ولكن الشيء الأجمل هو اللقطات التي التقطت
from the Triton submersible.
من غواصة التريتون.
What was not mentioned in the Discovery documentary
وذكر في قناة ديسكفوري الوثائقية
was that the bait squid that Dr. Kubodera used,
أن الطعم الذي استخدمه د.كوبوديرا للحبار
a one-meter long diamondback squid
كان حبّارا طوله متر
had a light attached to it, a squid jig
مثبّت به ضوء، رقصة حبار
of the type that longline fishermen use,
من النوع الذي يستخدمه الصيادون الذين يصيدون بالخيوط الصنارية الطويلة
and I think it was this light
و أعتقد أن هذا الضوء
that brought the giant in.
هو السبب في جذب العملاق.
Now, what you're seeing
والآن، ما ترونه
is the intensified camera's view under red light,
هو منظر مكثّف من كاميرا تحت الضوء الأحمر
and that's all Dr. Kubodera could see when the giant comes in here.
وهذا كل ما استطاع د.كيبوديرا رؤيته عندما يقترب العملاق هنا.
And then he got so excited,
ومن ثم أصبح متحمساً جداً
he turned on his flashlight because he wanted to see better,
وأشعل مصباحه لأنّه أراد أن يراه بشكل أفضل،
and the giant didn't run away,
و لم يهرب العملاق بعيداً،
so he risked turning on the white lights on the submersible,
وخاطر بالتفاته باتجاه الضوء الأبيض في الغواصة،
bringing a creature of legend
وبذلك تحوّل الكائن من أسطورة
from the misty history into high-resolution video.
من التاريخ الغامض إلى فيديو عالي الدقة.
It was absolutely breathtaking,
كان الأمر مذهلا تماما،
and had this animal had its feeding tentacles intact
ولدى هذا الحيوان مخالب للتغذية سليمة
and fully extended,
و ممدة بالكامل،
it would have been as tall as a two-story house.
وقد يكون طولها مطول بيت مكوّن من دورين.
How could something that big
كيف يمكن لشيء بهذا الكبر
live in our ocean and yet remain unfilmed until now?
أن يعيش في محيطنا ولم يصوّر حتى الآن؟
We've only explored about five percent of our ocean.
نحن لم نكتشف إلا حوالي 5٪ من محيطنا.
There are great discoveries yet to be made down there,
و هناك اكتشافات عظيمة ستظهر هناك،
fantastic creatures representing millions of years of evolution
مخلوقات مذهلة تمثل ملايين السنين من التطور
and possibly bioactive compounds
ومن المحتمل أنّ المركبات الحيوية النشطة
that could benefit us in ways that we can't even yet imagine.
قد تنفعنا بطرق لا يمكن تخيلها.
Yet we have spent only a tiny fraction
ولكننا أنفقنا نسبة ضئيلة
of the money on ocean exploration
من المال في استكشاف المحيطات.
that we've spent on space exploration.
مقارنة بالمال الذي أنفقناه في استكشاف الفضاء.
We need a NASA-like organization for ocean exploration,
نحتاج إلى منظمة مثل ناسا لاستكشاف الفضاء،
because we need to be exploring and protecting
لأننا نحتاج أن نستكشف و نحمي
our life support systems here on Earth.
نظام دعم الحياة على الأرض.
We need — thank you. (Applause)
نحتاج ـــ شكراً. (تصفيق)
Exploration is the engine that drives innovation.
الاستكشاف هو المحرك الذي يقود الابتكار.
Innovation drives economic growth.
و الابتكار يقود النمو الاقتصادي.
So let's all go exploring,
لنذهب و نستكشف
but let's do it in a way that doesn't scare the animals away,
و لنقوم بذلك بطريقة لا تخيف الحيوانات و تبعدها،
or, as Mike deGruy once said,
أو، كما قال مايك ديجري:
"If you want to get away from it all
"إذا أردت أن تهرب من كل شيء،
and see something you've never seen,
وترى شيئاً لم تره من قبل،
or have an excellent chance of seeing something that no one's ever seen,
أو أن تحظى بفرصة ممتازة لأن ترى شيـئاً لم يره أحداً من قبل،
get in a sub."
اركب غوّاصة."
He should have been with us for this adventure.
كان ينبغي أن يكون معنا في هذه المغامرة.
We miss him.
اشتقنا له.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)